<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Rabans resolution against drunkennes and whoredome vvhich are the chiefe occasions of the breach of Gods Sabbath, and consequently of our damnation.</title>
            <author>Raban, Edward, d. 1658.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1622</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 11 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10312</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20597</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S1283</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">22102603</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 22102603</idno>
            <idno type="VID">25055</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10312)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 25055)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1734:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Rabans resolution against drunkennes and whoredome vvhich are the chiefe occasions of the breach of Gods Sabbath, and consequently of our damnation.</title>
                  <author>Raban, Edward, d. 1658.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16]+ p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>E. Raban,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[St. Andrews :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1622]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: lacks all except signature B; bound and filmed out of order.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambrdige University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sins --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Temperance --  Biblical teaching --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:25055:1"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
                  <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap> cleanneſſe of lyfe; commanding us to abſtaine from <hi>Drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> which bringeth us for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde unto <hi>Whoredome:</hi> and when wee haue once embraced theſe, they leade us captiue, unto <hi>the breach of Gods Sabbath:</hi> to bee diſobedient unto our Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, Magiſtrates, and Paſtors: to ſteale: to murder: to ſweare, and forſweare: yea, to become Idolaters, and blaſphemers of Gods Name, &amp;c. as ſhall bee ſhowne hereafter, God willing, by ſufficient Teſtimonies, as well out of Gods worde, as alſo from the Wrytings of holie and learned Authors: together with manifeſt Examples; of the which ſome haue happened eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:25055:1"/>in our dayes. But firſt of all, let us come along the Borders of the Byble, and take a view how the Plague of <hi>Drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> hath miſerablie infected ſome even of GODS deareſt Saincts, from the beginning.</p>
            <p>Then to begin with <hi>Noah<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> who firſt after the Flood plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a Vineyarde, was firſt <hi>drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken,</hi> and curſed his ſonne <hi>Cham,</hi> becauſe hee mocked him, when he ſaw him lye ſleeping unco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered. <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 9.21.</p>
            <p>What excuſe can our <hi>Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kards</hi> now adayes, drawe from <hi>Noah?</hi> he knew not the quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the Grape, but was beg<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with the juyce thereof; and that after his weariſome buſines
<pb facs="tcp:25055:2"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:25055:2"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:25055:3"/>no doubt: and yet for his fault he eſcapeth not, but is puniſhed with the deriſion of his owne ſonne, his ſonne is accurſed, and the whole generation of the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naanites</hi> alſo accurſed of God for his ſake: beholde, <hi>Noahs</hi> indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent <hi>drunkenneſſe</hi> is the origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall hereof: And ſhall we then be blameleſſe, who wilfully, wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinglie, &amp; of ſet purpoſe, drinke our ſelues <hi>drunken?</hi> giving it the name of <hi>Merrineſſe, Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fellowſhip,</hi> &amp;c. No, ſurelie, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept wee forſake and deteſt our vylde <hi>Drunkenneſſe,</hi> not onelie ſhall our fleſh and blood (and all godly Men) hold us in deriſion; but God Himſelfe will laugh us to ſcorne, the Earth ſhall bee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed
<pb facs="tcp:25055:5"/>for our ſakes, and at the Great Day of the Lord we ſhall deſcende downward, &amp; receiue a portion in the Lake which is alreadie prepared with fire and brimſtone, for the Devill, who ſhall bee accompanied with the impenitent <hi>Drunkardes, Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lots, Sabbath-breakers Swea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers,</hi> &amp;c. Therefore, in the Name of God, let us joyn hands with the holy Ghoſt (leaving off all <hi>Vncleanneſſe</hi>) and ſanctifie the Lords Sabbath here; ſo ſhall we poſſeſſe thoſe glorious Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions hereafter which Hee hath prepared for us from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the worlde.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lots</hi> two Daughters beguiled their Father: they made him
<pb facs="tcp:25055:6"/>
               <hi>drunken:</hi> and there-upon hee committed moſte abhominable Inceſt, &amp; begot his own daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters with childe: and, though hee knew not of it, yet was hee puniſhed in that his untimelie ſeede: (the ſeede of <hi>Drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> we may call it) for the el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt daughter bare the father of the <hi>Moabites,</hi> and the younger the father of the <hi>Ammonites;</hi> who as they were begotten in <hi>drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken inceſtuous whoredome,</hi> ſo were they, and their poſteritie, vylde and wicked. <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 19. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 32.33.34.35. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Lord Himſelfe maketh <hi>Drunkenneſſe</hi> a marke, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the unholie are known from the holie, and the unclean from
<pb facs="tcp:25055:6"/>the cleane. <hi>Leviticus, Chap.</hi> 10. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 9.10.</p>
            <p>And vvhat hapned unto <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bal,</hi> I pray you, after his <hi>drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſſe?</hi> The Scripture ſaith, that he was <hi>verie drunken:</hi> and he never roſe againe: for within ten dayes after, the Lord ſmote that <hi>drunken gluttonous churle</hi> that he died. 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 38.</p>
            <p>When <hi>David</hi> had committed adulterie with <hi>Vriahs</hi> wife, hee ſent for her husband from the Campe, and made him <hi>drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken:</hi> thinking that <hi>drunkennes</hi> would provoke him to <hi>Luſt,</hi> to goe downe to his houſe, &amp; lye with his wife, &amp;c. But becauſe <hi>drunkennes</hi> prevailed not to cover adulterie, murder procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded:
<pb facs="tcp:25055:7"/>yea, murder after murder: ſo that the ſworde never depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from <hi>Davids</hi> houſe. 2. <hi>Sam. Verſ.</hi> 10.</p>
            <p>It is to bee marked, that the wiſe king <hi>Salomon</hi> often joyneth <hi>Whoredome,</hi> with <hi>Drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe;</hi> ſtrong drink, with ſtrange women, &amp;c. as unſeparable companions: and ſaieth, that thoſe are the wayes which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy even kinges, and cauſeth them to forget Gods decree, &amp; to change the judgement of the children of affliction. <hi>Prov.</hi> 23. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 27.28.29.30.31.32.33. And <hi>Chap.</hi> 31. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 3.4.5.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Ieſus Syrach,</hi> in his booke called <hi>Eccleſiaſticus,</hi> rayleth out moſte bitterlie againſt the vyces
<pb facs="tcp:25055:7"/>of <hi>Drun<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>enneſſe, Gluttonie, Leacherie,</hi> &amp;c. ſaying, that they bring men to povertie, make them impudent, to forget God, &amp; all goo<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> manners, pleniſheth men full of <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>glie diſeaſes in this life: and in the ende bringeth both bodie and ſoule into Hell fire. <hi>Syrach</hi> 19.3. and 23.6. and 31.12.</p>
            <p>The Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> thunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring out the threatnings of the Lord againſt His people, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braydeth them eſpeciallie with <hi>Drunkenneſſe,</hi> and maketh it the verie roote of all <hi>Miſchiefe,</hi> even amongſt men of every vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation: for hee ſpareth neyther King nor Biſhop, Prophet nor Puritane, Prieſt nor Laicke, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter
<pb facs="tcp:25055:8"/>nor Servant: but ſaith, they all goe aſtraye through ſtrong <hi>Drinke,</hi> and are even ſwallo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed up with <hi>Drunkenneſſe. <hi>If any ſhould be offended hereat, I trust hee will blame the Prophet for his downe-ſetting, and excuſe mee for my repetition: for it is not mine inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to cavill with any, nor to moue them to wrath: but rather to make my ſelfe, and others, abhorre</hi> Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſſe. <hi>Loe, reade the places: Iſaiah, Chap.</hi>
               </hi> 5. <hi>verſ.</hi> 11.12.22.23. And <hi>Chap.</hi> 22. <hi>verſ.</hi> 13.14. And <hi>Chap.</hi> 28. <hi>verſ.</hi> 7.8. And <hi>Chap.</hi> 56. <hi>verſ.</hi> 10.11.12.</p>
            <p>Now take but a ſlender view what the prophet <hi>Ezekiel</hi> ſays of <hi>Dru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kennes, Gluttonie, Pryde,</hi> and <hi>Ydleneſſe,</hi> together with
<pb facs="tcp:25055:8"/>
               <hi>Whoredome,</hi> thoſe fiue ſiſters; in the 16. chapt. of his Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie: and ſo let us goe on, and ſee what <hi>Daniel</hi> ſayth of <hi>Drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> and the reſt of the holie Prophets.</p>
            <p>It is then manifeſt by <hi>Daniel,</hi> that God, even our owne God, is a mercifull Lord, ſlow to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and readie to forgiue: yea, in His wrath He thinketh on mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie. But if His mercies, loving kindneſſe, and wonderfull great benefits, which Hee beſtoweth upon us, from time to time, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vayle not with us; then wee muſt underſtand that He is righ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teous, and is forced (thorow our ingratitude) to enter into judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with us. As we ſee by the
<pb facs="tcp:25055:9"/>example of many here &amp; there thorow the whole Byble: and in this place by <hi>Belſhazzar,</hi> king of <hi>Babylon,</hi> who ſucceeded to the kingdome when <hi>Nebuchadnezar</hi> was driven from <hi>Babel,</hi> &amp; from the fellowſhip of men, and was faine to eate graſſe with beaſtes, and abide heate, colde, and wet, till his haire grewe like Eagles feathers, and his nayles like the clawes of Fowles? this miſerie came unto him, no doubt, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row <hi>Wantonneſſe, Drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſſe, Gluttonie,</hi> and <hi>Whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome:</hi> for thoſe are the Chaines where-with Satan bindeth the worlde, and draweth us from the true ſervice of our God, and maketh us abjectes, and ſlaues
<pb facs="tcp:25055:3"/>unto ſinne, &amp; at laſt to become like himſelfe, even damned for ever. Thus much concerning <hi>Nebuchadnezar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now let us goe on, unto <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhazzar,</hi> of whom wee ſpake be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: and let us beholde what kinde of <hi>Ryot, Gluttonie,</hi> and <hi>Drunkenneſſe</hi> he uſed, &amp; what was the ſucceſſe thereof. The Scripture ſayth, he made a Feaſt unto no leſſe than a thouſande Princes: and that hee drunke much wine in their companie: yea, till hee became <hi>drunken.</hi> And then forſooth no Veſſels could ſerue him to drinke in, but thoſe of Golde and Silver, which his Grandfather <hi>Nebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chadnezar</hi> had taken out of the
<pb facs="tcp:25055:4"/>Temple of the Lord in <hi>Hieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem:</hi> thoſe, I ſay, he cauſed bring before him, filled them with ſtrong Drinke, and he, his prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, wiues, concubines, and har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lots dranke, and were beaſtlie <hi>drunken:</hi> then thought they no more on the God of Heaven: but rather in contempt of Him, with wide throats they prayſed the gods which were made with mens hands, of Golde, Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, Braſſe, Yron, Wood, and of Stone. But what followed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this <hi>Drunkenneſſe?</hi> As I take it, the drinke was not yet digeſted when the king was ſlaine, his houſe divided, and a miſerable ende hapned on the whole <hi>drunken rout,</hi> I war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rand
<pb facs="tcp:25055:4"/>you. <hi>Daniel, Chap.</hi> 4. <hi>verſ.</hi> 30. And <hi>Chap.</hi> 5. <hi>verſ.</hi> 1.2.3.4.30.31.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hoſea</hi> propheſieth, that there ſhall be like people, like prieſt: they ſhall <hi>eate,</hi> but not bee ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied: they ſhall commit <hi>Adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie,</hi> but not increaſe: <hi>Whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> &amp; wine taketh away their heart: the ſpirit of <hi>Fornication</hi> cauſeth them to erre: they ſtill goe <hi>a whoring:</hi> therefore their daughters ſhall be <hi>Harlots,</hi> and their ſpouſes <hi>Whores:</hi> &amp; their <hi>Drunkenneſſe</hi> ſtinketh. But I hope there are no ſuch prieſtes in this Age: if there bee, I dare ſay they are amongſt the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> but not amongſt us. <hi>But I pray you reade the</hi> 4.5. <hi>and</hi> 6. <hi>Chapters
<pb facs="tcp:25055:5"/>of Hoſea, for in them is ſo much ſayd of Priests, that I thinke a Ieſuit will <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> enough adoe to expound them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Prophet <hi>Ioel</hi> biddeth the <hi>Drunkardes</hi> to awake, and in ſteade of their <hi>drunken</hi> pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyme and laughter, to howle, and lament: for, ſayth hee, yee haue made ſale of Gods people: and the price which ye get, yee beſtow it on <hi>Harlots,</hi> and on <hi>Wine,</hi> that ye may drinke, and bee <hi>drunken:</hi> but woe bee unto you, for the drinke ſhall be pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led from your mouth, &amp; a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den deſtruction ſhall come up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you. <hi>Ioel, Chap.</hi> 1. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 5. And <hi>Chap.</hi> 3. <hi>verſ.</hi> 3.4.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Micah,</hi> in his 2. <hi>Chapt.</hi> threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the wanton <hi>Drunkardes, and</hi> 
               <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
                  <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
